Guide to the University of Chicago Office of the President, Beadle Administration Records 1916-1968
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Beadle Administration. Records
1916-1968
219.5 linear feet (424 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
This collection contains records of the University of Chicago Office of the President, covering the administration of George W. Beadle, who served as President from 1961-1968. Included are administrative records such as correspondence, reports, publications, budgets and personnel material.
Information on Use
Access
Series I-V, and Series VII are open for research, with no restrictions.
Series VI: Appointments and Budgets, is restricted until 2018.
Historical Note
George Wells Beadle (1903-1989) was the son of Chauncey Elmer Beadle, a farmer, and Hattie Albro. Beadle was educated at the Wahoo High School in Nebraska and may have become a farmer if one of his teachers at school had not directed him towards science and persuaded him to go to the College of Agriculture at Lincoln, Nebraska. There he took up the new field of genetics and continued on to receive his Ph.D. from Cornell University.
Beadle taught biology at Harvard, Stanford and the California Institute of Technology before coming to the University of Chicago. During his time at Stanford, Beadle began his collaboration with Edward L. Tatum. Beadle and Tatum worked to establish the relationship between genes and enzymes in the bread mold Neurospora, which would earn them the 1958 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.
In 1960, Beadle was elected Chancellor of the University of Chicago and, in autumn of the same year, President of the University. Beadle served as President and Professor of biology from 1961-1968. These were turbulent years of growth and change for universities across the country. Despite calls for universities to become centers for social and political action, Beadle held the University of Chicago steady to its traditional values of research and intellectual excellence. Beadle increased the size of the faculty, raised the average salary, and doubled campus expenditures. The three year development campaign reached its goal of $160 million and many new buildings were erected on campus. Beadle led the university through student protests concerning racial segregation in university housing policy as well as Vietnam protests against university compliance with government regulations requiring reports on the academic ranking of male students for draft purposes.
While president of the University of Chicago, Beadle continued his interest in genetics and grew corn behind his house and in other plots near campus, occasionally being mistaken for a University gardener. Beadle retired from the Presidency on his 65th birthday. He accepted the directorship of the Institute for Biomedical Research of the American Medical Association which he moved to campus, where he remained to teach and continue experiments with corn for some years. He was named William E. Wrather Professor of Biology from 1969-1975 and retired to Pomona, California with his wife Muriel in 1982.
Scope Note
The records of the Office of the President, Beadle Administration, represent the activities of George Wells Beadle as President, his immediate circle of Central Administration associates (including particularly the work of Edward H. Levi as Vice-President), and personnel in the University of Chicago's divisions, departments, committees, and other administrative units. The collection thus constitutes not only documentation of the Office of the President, but a varied record of the administrative workings of the university.
While most of the documents in the collection date from the years in which Beadle served as President, material dating to earlier administrations can also be found - staff of the office often collected such material for internal research, or to provide historical or biographical context for a current topic.
The collection is divided into seven series, each of which is organized into alphabetical or chronological files. This organization, including the file headings themselves, is generally consistent with the original arrangement of files kept by staff in the Office of the President.
Series I, General Files, contains a variety of correspondence, publications, reports, minutes and other administrative material. The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. File headings include personal names, administrative units, and topical terms. Headings are sometimes very general ("Germany") while others are quite precise ("United States, House of Representatives Sub-Committee on Public Health and Safety, questionnaire"). Oversize material from this series has been transferred to Series VII: Oversize Material, Box 424
Series II, Buildings, contains correspondence, blueprints, reports, publications and administrative documents pertaining to university buildings. Large blueprints from this series have been transferred to Architectural Drawings Collection in the University of Chicago Archives.
Series III, Development, contains a variety of correspondence, publications, reports, minutes and other administrative material relating to the Development campaign of the University. Oversized materials from this series have been moved to Series VII: Oversize Material, Boxes 420-423. Additional material related to Development is found in Series I, filed under "Development" or the specific names or titles associated with varying development projects.
Series IV, Invitations, is arranged chronologically. This series contains invitations sent to Beadle and other representatives of the university. The invitations are from organizations across the globe range from university anniversaries to installations of new presidents.
Series V, Trustees, is arranged alphabetically. This series contains material reporting the activities of the university's trustees and their Board, as well as material generated by trustees' work.
Series VI, Appointments and Budgets, contains budgets and letters of appointment, arranged alphabetically. Related correspondence, notes and drafts are also filed with appointments and budgets
Series VII: Oversize Material, contains large files and items transferred from Series I and II.
Most researchers will find it necessary to browse or keyword-search the inventory in order to identify files relevant to a specific subject. For example, a study of student protests might involve consultation of files headed "Demonstrations," "Selective Service," "Student draft demonstration," "Student government," " Students for a Democratic Society," "Vietnam," and so on.
Correspondence of key administrators is also distributed across the collection, some of it located under the name of the individual and some under the name of a department, school, or other institutional unit. To search for the correspondence of important administrators such as Edward H. Levi or Fairfax M. Cone, the researcher will need to be aware of which administrative responsibilities each held and locate headings in the inventory related to those roles.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Beadle, George W. Papers
Levi, Edward H. Papers
University of Chicago. Board of Trustees. Minutes
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Harper, Judson and Burton Administrations. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Mason Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Hutchins Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Kimpton Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Levi Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Wilson Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Gray Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Sonnenschein Administration. Records
Subject Headings
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989; Levi, Edward Hirsch, 1911-; University of Chicago -- Administration; University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago -- Presidents; University of Chicago. Office of the President
INVENTORY
- Series IA: General Files, A-H
  - A-, general, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Academic Freedom, (General Comment) Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, binder, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, binder, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, general material, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, de Huszar, George B., 1949-1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, university statements, 1935-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Academic Freedom, Illinois Seditious Activities Investigating Commission, university statements, 1935-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Academic Freedom, loyalty oaths and affidavits, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Academic Freedom, "Red-Ucators at the U. of C.", bulletin issued by National Council for American Education, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Academic Freedom, transcript hearings of seditious activities, Broyles Commission, April 21-23 and May 19, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Academy for Policy Study, Executive Council meeting, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Academy of South Asian Art History, project for an, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ACTION, Program for the American City, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Admissions and Aid, Office of, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Admissions, Office of, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Admissions, Office of, Faculty Committee to Advise on Guidelines in Handling Admissions, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Admissions, Office of, the College, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Admissions, Office of, policies and practices, 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Adult Education, Board of, meetings, minutes and agendas, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Adult Education, Board of, membership, 1961-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Adult Education Council of Greater Chicago, 1962-1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Adult Tutorial Education Program, proposed by Mr. J. Schwab, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Advanced Research Project Agency (ARPA), 1961-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Council, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Advertising Council, American roundtable meetings, 1958-1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Advertising Council, Public Policy Committee, George W Beadle membership, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Aid, requests for, 1960-1968 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Africa, 1961-1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - African and American Universities Program, 1961-1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - African Scholarship Program of American Universities, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - African Studies Association, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - African Studies, Committee on, 1963-1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Afro-American Studies and Culture, University Affiliated Institute of, proposed, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Akron, University of, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Al-, general, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Alaska, University of, 1962-1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Albert, A.A., "On the Administration of Research in a University," 1966 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Alcohol permits, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Allied Arts Corporation, 1961-1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Alumni, 75th anniversary, Alumni Conference on the College, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Alumni, 75th anniversary, Conference of the Responsibilities of Communication, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Affairs, Office of, directorship, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Alumni Affairs, Office of, Regional Office, Eastern, newsletter, 1960-1966 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Alumni Affairs, Office of, Regional Office, Eastern, New York City Office, 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Alumni Affairs, Office of, Regional Office, Western, San Francisco Office, 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Alumni Affairs, Office of, Regional Office, Western, Los Angeles Office, 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association, 1961-1965 (Box 8, Folder 2-6)
  - Alumni Association, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  - Alumni Association, 1st annual cabinet meetings and tribute to Mr. E. H. Levi, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Association, alumni directories, 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Association, alumni resource list, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Alumni Association, audit reports, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association, cabinet, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association, chapters, University of Chicago Club of Rhode Island, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Association, citations and medal, 1961-1967 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Alumni Association, Emeritus Club, 1964-1967 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Association, Matisse exhibition and supper, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Association of the College, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Association, School of Social Service Administration, 1963-1967 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Association, U-High, 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Alumni Association, U-High constitution and by-laws, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Association, U-High reunion, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Alumni bulletins, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Alumni bulletins, Tower Topics, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Alumni campaigns, 1961-1966 (Box 11, Folder 4-9)
  - Alumni campaigns, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Alumni campaigns, closing reports, 1961-1966 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Alumni, Chancellor's Conferences, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Alumni, Denver campaign, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Alumni, eastern regional office, 1961-1963 (Box 12, Folder 5-7)
  - Alumni, eastern regional office, 1964-1968 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Alumni Foundation, Board of Directors, general, 1961-1963 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Foundation, Board of Directors, membership, 1961-1965 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Foundation, Harold H. Swift statement for alumni pamphlet, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Foundation, William Rainey Harper Club, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Fund, 1961-1965 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
  - Alumni Fund, 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Alumni Fund, Detroit, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Fund, gifts campaigns, reports and analyses, 1960-1963 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Fund, Portland, Oregon, 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Alumni, general, 1960-1963 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
  - Alumni, general, 1964-1968 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Alumni, George W. Beadle trips west, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Alumni, Graduate School of Business, 1964-1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Alumni, joint dinner meeting of Association Cabinet and Fund Board, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Alumni, Law School, 1960-1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Office, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Alumni, mailings, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Alumni, medical, 1962-1968 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Alumni meetings, 1957-1962 (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
  - Alumni meetings, 1963-1966 (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
  - Alumni meetings, George W. Beadle, the Egyptologists, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Alumni meetings, George W. Beadle, Milton Friedman, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Alumni, President's fund campaign, 1964-1966 (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Alumni reunion, 1965-1968 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Alumni, Salt Lake City, Utah, Edwin Firmage, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Alumni trustees, proposal, 1966-1968 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Alumni, west coast region, 1958-1968 (Box 17, Folder 7-11)
  - Am-, general, 1963-1966 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - American Academy of Achievement, 1961-1967 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1962-1968 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, membership of University faculty, 1962-1967 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, nominations of University faculty, 1964-1967 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Warren Weaver's book on foundation, 1964-1967 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - American Academy of Benares, India, 1965-1968 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1961-1967 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1961-1966 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - American Anthropological Association, 1962-1967 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1962-1968 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, constitution and by-laws, annual dinner, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1964- 1968 (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, bulletins, 1963-1968 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers, 1950-1967 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business, 1963-1968 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - American Association for Higher Education, 1961-1968 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Immunologists, 1948-1962 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - American Association of Land Grant Colleges, 1961-1962 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - American Association of Theological Schools, 1959-1965 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Universities, delegation to Britain (Sussex, London and York), July 1966 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1961-1968 (Box 20, Folder 7-8)
  - American Association of University Professors, LAK deposition, Marshall and Kammerer cases, 1958-1964 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - American Association of University Professors, study of salary scales, 1961-1965 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - American Association of University Professors, study of salary scales, 1963-1968 (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
  - American Association of University Women, 1961-1966 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - American Astronautical Society, 1965-1967 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - American Astronomical Society, 1957-1967 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - American Bankers Association, 1963-1968 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - American Baptist Convention, 1960-1965 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
  - American Baptist Convention, relationship with the University of Chicago, 1962-1967 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Animal Care, Committee on, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Animal Care, Office of, Thompson Research Foundation Dog Conditioning Facility, 1963-1968 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - American Chemical Society, 1961-1967 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1962-1968 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - American College of Cardiology, 1966-1968 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - American College Health Association, 1961-1968 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - American College of Radiology, 1961-1965 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - American Conservatory Theatre Act, 1965-1966 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education, 1961-1964 (Box 23, Folder 5-8)
  - American Council on Education, 1965-1968 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - American Council on Education, 46th annual meeting, Chicago, October 3-5 1962 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education, 46th annual meeting, Washington, D.C., October 2-4, 1963 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education, 47th annual meeting, San Francisco, September 30-October 11964 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education, 48th annual meeting, Washington D.C., October 6-8 1965 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education, academic administration internship program, 1964-1968 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, Board of Directors, 1962-1965 (Box 25, Folder 2-3)
  - American Council on Education, Board of Directors, meeting, 1963-1964 (Box 25, Folder 4-6)
  - American Council on Education, Board of Directors, meeting, 1965 (Box 26, Folder 1-3)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on Academic Affairs, 1962-1968 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on Federal Relations, 1962-1966 (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on Federal Relations, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, Committee on Sponsored Research, 1962-1965 (Box 27, Folder 2-4)
  - American Council on Education, Committee on Taxation, 1964-1968 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education, Executive Committee meeting, 1961 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education, "Expanding Opportunities," 1965-1967 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education, fiftieth anniversary, October 11, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education, Institute for College and University Administrators, 1965-1968 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - American Council on Education, questions on financing medical school and related health professions, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - American Council on Education, questionnaire, data bank for higher education, proposed, 1966 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, reports, surveys, booklets, 1960-1967 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education, special meeting, 1961 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education, survey of salaries of new faculty, 1967-1968 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - American Council for Emigres in the Professions, Inc., 1960-1967 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Higher Education, Higher Education and National Affairs, 1961-1965 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1961-1968 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - American Federation of Clinical Research, 1961 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - American Foundation for Tropical Medicine, 1961-1962 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - American Friends of Hebrew University, 1962 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - American, general f-s, 1961-1966 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - American Geophysical Union, 1964-1966 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - American Hospital Association, 1961-1968 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - America India Dispensary (AID), 1965-1967 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - American Indian Charter Convention, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
  - American Institute of Indian Studies, 1961-1968 (Box 29, Folder 3-6)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1947-1968 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1961-1968 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - American Judicature Society, 1963-1968 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - American Marketing Association, 1964-1965 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - American Mathematical Society, 1963-1967 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - American Medical Association (AMA), 1957-1964-1966 (Box 30, Folder 6-8)
  - American Medical Association, Institute for Biomedical Research, 1966-1968 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - American Medical Association, papers on medical education, 1961-1966 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - American Meat Institute, 1963-1964 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - American Meat Institute, annual meetings, 1961-1963 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - American Meat Institute, building, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - American Meat Institute, building alterations, space, 1960-1965 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - American Meat Institute, early history, Institute of Meat Packing, 1940-1965 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - American Meat Institute Foundation, 1961-1963 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - American Meat Institute Foundation, agreements and termination of arrangements, 1944-1964 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - American Meat Institute, Joint Administration Committee, 1961 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - American Meteorological Society, 1962-1967 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - American Museum of Health, 1962 (Box 32, Folder 4)